<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel><title>Gregg's MOTD</title><link>http://www.szumowski.org/index.html</link>
<description>Tips & Tricks that I've Encountered Over the Years...</description><language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 17:34:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 17:34:46 -0400</pubDate>
<atom:link href="http://www.szumowski.org/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item><title>
Git: Committing to a Different Branch
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Let’s imaging that you’ve made some changes to files in your work
directory and then realized that you aren’t in the correct branch. Now
you want to get the changes you’ve made to the right branch but no
change the current branch. What do you do?</p>
<p>There is no <em>git</em> command to do this but you can use the
<em>git stash</em> command to fix this.</p>
<p>This involves:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Using the <em>git stash</em> command to temporarily store our
changes elsewhere,</li>
<li>Checkout the correct branch, and</li>
<li>“Unstash” the changes to the correct branch.</li>
</ol>
<p>Let’s say that we’ve made some changes in our repository’s
new-release branch but they should have been made in the new-feature
branch.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>git stash</code><br/>
<code>git checkout new-feature</code><br/>
<code>git stash pop</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>We can now perform a commit, and update this branch.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>git commit -a -m "Updated functions in new-feature branch."</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_git.html'>git</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/git-committing-to-a-different-branch12884.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./git-committing-to-a-different-branch12884.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2023 17:34:40 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Printing from Virtualbox
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>If you want to set up your system so that you can access your Linux
host’s printer from a Windows VirtualBox client then:</p>
<p><strong>On Your Linux Host</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Install your printer driver. Get your printer working on your host
first.</li>
<li>Install <em>CUPS</em> if it is not already installed.</li>
<li>Add your printer to <em>CUPS</em> at
<code>http://localhost:631/admin</code>.</li>
<li>Set your virtual machine’s Network to <em>Bridged Adapter
(eth0)</em> in Settings and connect the cable as necessary (Advanced
menu).<br />
</li>
<li>Startup VirtualBox.<br />
</li>
<li>In a terminal, enter <code>ifconfig</code> to list your current
network settings and copy down your host’s (eth0) address or you can
optionally access this address using Network Manager.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>On You Windows Client</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Add a new Network printer in “<em>Printers and Faxes</em>” from the
<em>Control Panel</em></li>
<li>Enter the URL address of your host’s printer, i.e.,
<code>http://192.168.0.2:631/printers/Your_printer's_name</code>. You
need the <code>:631</code> after your host’s address as this is the port
that <em>CUPS</em> listens to. The <em>Your_printer’s_name</em> is the
name of the printer you added to <em>CUPS</em>.</li>
</ol>
<p>If you can’t establish a connection then check your firewall
settings.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_virtualbox.html'>virtualbox</a>, <a href='tag_printing.html'>printing</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/printing-from-virtualbox30746.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./printing-from-virtualbox30746.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 17:42:45 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Installing and Using sbotools in Slackware 15.0
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Slackware was the first Linux distribution that I ever used but I was
always curious and did a lot of distro-hopping from Slackware, Caldera,
Turbo Linux, Mandrake, Red Hat, Ubuntu, multiple Ubuntu derivatives,
then Fedora for quite a while until I finally settled on…(drum roll
please)…Slackware! Yeah, I’ve come full circle.</p>
<p>One of the reasons why I was doing so much hopping around is that I
was never really happy with something about the distribution that I was
currently using. Maybe it was the default colors (Ubuntu, come on with
all of that orange stuff), choice of default software, difficulty with
setting it up. Whatever. With Slackware it was always the (lack of) a
decent package management system. That is until I found “sbotools”.</p>
<p>Yeah, slackpkg is there. So are a few others, like (list a few of
them here). But the lack of a distribution that didn’t have dependency
management in its package manager is a real pain in the backside.</p>
<p>So what’s the big deal? Well, one of the points of running Slackware
is installing packages that you choose to install and not letting the
package manager run amuck and automatically select and install a full
list of dependencies without letting the user know what they are and
what they do. That’s where sbotools comes in.</p>
<p>Klaatu talks about <a
href="https://pink-mist.github.io/sbotools/">sbotools</a> in his Gnu
World Order Episode <a
href="https://gnuworldorder.info/audiophile/gnuWorldOrder_473_ogg.ogg">473</a>
so you can find more information about it in his review.</p>
<p>As sbotools is highly influenced by FreeBSD’s ports system and its
pkgtools, the interface will be more or less familiar to anyone familiar
with portupgrade, etc.</p>
<p>When you use sbotools it finds the dependencies for the software you
want to install and for each one, displays what it is, what it does, and
prompts you if you want to install it or not. Also, if the dependency
has optional parameters it asks you if you want to see them and gives
you a choice to modify them or not.</p>
<p>Now all of this is done in the console, which is another thing that I
like about sbotools. No fancy ncurses or GUI dialogs. Just a simple
console program which is handy if you’re using a <em>headless</em>
server.</p>
<p>Once you are done selecting your package and providing whatever
responses are required, sbotools downloads the Slackbuilds and the
source code from wherever it needs to and compiles the packages one by
one in the order required and installs them. If a compilation fails then
it asks you if you wish to continue or quit. Then you have the option to
try figuring out what went wrong but looking at the build logs or by
scrolling back on the console output.</p>
<p>The sbotools package is not a single program but a collection of
about a half a dozen programs that work very much like the BSD ports.
You have a tool to initialize and fetch the latest list of packages,
another to check to see if you need to update your locally installed
programs, another to search for them and one to install new
packages.</p>
<p>Installing sbotools is rather simple if you’re use to installing
packages by hand in Slackware. It comes as a tz package that you install
using the ‘installpkg’ command.</p>
<p>First you need to install the <a
href="https://pink-mist.github.io/sbotools/downloads//">sbotools</a>
package. Then you need to “sync” the SlackBuild repository to your
machine using the command:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># sbosnap fetch</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This will create a <em>git repository</em> of all of the SlackBuilds
supported by this tool (which is a lot). Now you can use the
<em>sbofind</em> command to search for a package.</p>
<p>Next we will run <em>sbocheck</em> to see if there are any updates
since the last time. In this case since this is the first time we’re
using it we shouldn’t expect anything new. The example below shows the
results when you do have new results:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># sbocheck</code><br/>
<code>Updating SlackBuilds tree...</code><br/>
<code>Updating files: 100% (44404/44404), done.</code><br/>
<code>HEAD is now at 49808a413d 20230729.1 global branch merge.</code><br/>
<code>Checking for updated SlackBuilds...</code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>plexmediaserver 1.32.5.7328_2632c9d3a  &lt;  needs updating (1.32.5.7349_8f4248874 from SBo)</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>A copy of the above result is kept in /var/log/sbocheck.log</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>If the above command indicates that there are updates then you can
initiate an upgrade using the following command:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># sboupgrade --all</code><br/>
<code>Checking for updated SlackBuilds...</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>OK, so now your repository is set up. Let’s use it.</p>
<p>Suppose we want to find a software package that can read guitar
tabs:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># sbofind guitar</code><br/>
<code>SBo:    tuxguitar 1.5.1</code><br/>
<code>Path:   /usr/sbo/repo/audio/tuxguitar</code><br/>
<code></code><br/> <code>SBo:    guitarix 0.44.1</code><br/>
<code>Path:   /usr/sbo/repo/audio/guitarix</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>We received two results. Let’s query their details:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># sbofind -r guitarix</code><br/>
<code>SBo:    guitarix 0.44.1</code><br/>
<code>Path:   /usr/sbo/repo/audio/guitarix</code><br/>
<code>README:</code><br/>
<code>guitarix (virtual guitar amplifier for jack)</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>guitarix offers the range of sounds you would expect from a</code><br/>
<code>full-featured universal guitar-amp. You can get crisp clean-sounds,</code><br/>
<code>nice overdrive, fat distortion and a diversity of crazy sounds never</code><br/>
<code>heard before. Guitarix can be used as a standalone application, as</code><br/>
<code>LADSPA plugins, or as LV2 plugins.</code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>For 32-bit x86, a CPU with SSE instructions is required. For other</code><br/>
<code>architectures, SSE will be used if available.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>meterbridge is an optional runtime dependency.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>Starting with version 0.35.4, guitarix's 'Online presets' feature no</code><br/>
<code>longer requires webkitgtk. See README.online for more information.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>This package uses POSIX filesystem capabilities to execute with</code><br/>
<code>elevated privileges (required for realtime audio processing). This</code><br/>
<code>may be considered a security/stability risk. Please read</code><br/>
<code>http://www.slackbuilds.org/caps/ for more information. To disable</code><br/>
<code>capabilities, pass SETCAP=no to the script.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>root@slacker:~# sbofind -r tuxguitar</code><br/>
<code>SBo:    tuxguitar 1.5.1</code><br/>
<code>Path:   /usr/sbo/repo/audio/tuxguitar</code><br/>
<code>README:</code><br/>
<code>TuxGuitar is a multitrack guitar tablature editor and player written</code><br/>
<code>in Java-SWT. It can open GuitarPro, PowerTab, and TablEdit files.</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ah, looks like <em>tuxguitar</em> is the one we want. So let’s
install it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># sboinstall tuxguitar</code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>This is a SlackBuild to repackage the Azul's Zulu build of OpenJDK that</code><br/>
<code>is compliant with the Java SE 8 standard.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>Before installing this package please consider any other jdk's/jre's</code><br/>
<code>that you have already installed as they may cause conflicts with the</code><br/>
<code>PATH, JAVA_HOME and MANPATH variables.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>After installing the package you will need to logout/reboot your machine</code><br/>
<code>as it will add files to the /etc/profile.d folder.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>Note: zulu-openjdk8 does not have a browser plugin nor support for Java</code><br/>
<code>Network Launching Protocol (JNLP).</code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>Proceed with zulu-openjdk8? [y] n</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I already have a different version of Java installed so I will skip
this part</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>TuxGuitar is a multitrack guitar tablature editor and player written</code><br/>
<code>in Java-SWT. It can open GuitarPro, PowerTab, and TablEdit files.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/> <code>Proceed with tuxguitar? [y]</code><br/>
<code>tuxguitar added to install queue.</code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>Install queue: tuxguitar</code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>Are you sure you wish to continue? [y]</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>Slackware package /tmp/tuxguitar-1.5.1-x86_64-1_SBo.tgz created.</code><br/>
<code></code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>+==============================================================================</code><br/>
<code>| Installing new package /tmp/tuxguitar-1.5.1-x86_64-1_SBo.tgz</code><br/>
<code>+==============================================================================</code><br/>
<code></code><br/>
<code>Verifying package tuxguitar-1.5.1-x86_64-1_SBo.tgz.</code><br/>
<code>Installing package tuxguitar-1.5.1-x86_64-1_SBo.tgz:</code><br/>
<code>PACKAGE DESCRIPTION:</code><br/>
<code># tuxguitar (A Multitrack tablature editor and player)</code><br/>
<code>#</code><br/>
<code># TuxGuitar is a multitrack guitar tablature editor and player</code><br/>
<code># written in Java-SWT. It can open GuitarPro, PowerTab, and</code><br/>
<code># TablEdit files.</code><br/> <code>#</code><br/>
<code>Executing install script for tuxguitar-1.5.1-x86_64-1_SBo.tgz.</code><br/>
<code>Package tuxguitar-1.5.1-x86_64-1_SBo.tgz installed.</code><br/>
<code>Cleaning for tuxguitar-1.5.1...</code><br/>
<code>#</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>So, sboinstall will not install <em>any</em> package without telling
you first and it will describe what the packages does and if there are
any additional (optional or otherwise) command line parameters which it
will prompt you for.</p>
<p>Once you respond to the last prompt it will download and install (and
compile if necessary) all of the packages you requested. If it fails one
of the installations it will ask you if it should continue. If it
succeeds in installing all of the packages then you’re ready to start
using your software.</p>
<p>Each of the command line tools has it’s own manpage. Have fun!</p>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_slackware.html'>slackware</a>, <a href='tag_sbotools.html'>sbotools</a>, <a href='tag_slackbuilds.html'>slackbuilds</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/installing-and-using-sbotools-in-slackware-150.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./installing-and-using-sbotools-in-slackware-150.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 20:59:51 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Sorting Stuff in the VIM Buffer
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Suppose I have a file that I am editing in <em>vim</em> with the
following contents:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ cat file.txt</code><br/> <code>Red 4</code><br/>
<code>Blue 3</code><br/> <code>Green 1</code><br/>
<code>Orange 7</code><br/> <code>Black 8</code><br/>
<code>Yellow 6</code><br/> <code>Purple 2</code><br/>
<code>White 5</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>If I want to sort this data in <em>vim</em>, the first thing to do is
to format it into columns using the <em>column</em> command:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>:%!column -t</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which will put the data in the following format:</p>
<blockquote>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Red</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Blue</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Green</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Orange</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Black</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Yellow</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Purple</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>White</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</blockquote>
<p>Then we can sort on the 2nd column using the <em>sort</em>
command:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>:%!sort -k2nr</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which will update the buffer like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Black</td>
<td>8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Orange</td>
<td>7</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Yellow</td>
<td>6</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>White</td>
<td>5</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Red</td>
<td>4</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Blue</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Purple</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Green</td>
<td>1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</blockquote>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_vim.html'>vim</a>, <a href='tag_sort.html'>sort</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/sorting-stuff-in-the-vim-buffer26213.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./sorting-stuff-in-the-vim-buffer26213.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 16:40:42 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Using crontab
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Crontab is a utility found on Linux and UNIX that allows you to
schedule repetitive tasks on your system, like backups, updates,
etc.</p>
<p>The crontab command manages a table containing specially formatted
lines of text which is processed periodically by the system. Each line
consists of a “schedule” followed by one or more commands to be
processed at the scheduled time.</p>
<p>If you want to use the vim, emacs or nano editor for editing cron
jobs, then, set the following in your environment and in your
<code>~/.bash_profile</code> file:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>EDITOR=vim</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Then, to edit the default cron job, as <em>root</em> enter this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># crontab -e</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>If this is the first time you are editing the crontab, you may want
to put in the following header as a reminder or a template of the
format:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>#MINUTE(0-59) HOUR(0-23) DAYOFMONTH(1-31) MONTHOFYEAR(1-12) DAYOFWEEK(0-6)</code><br/>
<code>#Note that 0=Sun and 7=Sun</code><br/>
<code>#14,15 10 * * 0   /usr/bin/somecommmand  &gt;/dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The sample “commented out command” will run at 10:14 and 10:15 every
Sunday. There will be no <em>mail</em> sent to the user because of the
<code>&gt;/dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1</code> entry.</p>
<p>To list all cron jobs enter:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># crontab -l</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you’re logged in as <em>root</em> you can view or edit the crontab
entries of any of the users:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># crontab -l -u &lt;username&gt;</code><br/>
<code># crontab -e -u &lt;username&gt;</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can also run jobs on an hourly, daily, weekly or monthly basis by
adding shell scripts into one or more of the following directories:</p>
<ul>
<li>/etc/cron.hourly/</li>
<li>/etc/cron.daily/</li>
<li>/etc/cron.weekly/</li>
<li>/etc/cron.monthly/</li>
</ul>
<p>You can find out more information on the <em>crontab</em>
manpage.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_crontab.html'>crontab</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/using-crontab25619.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./using-crontab25619.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2023 14:26:41 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Ansible Cheatsheet
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>Ping all hosts:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ ansible all -i hosts -m ping</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ping a specific host:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ ansible raspberry-pi  -m ping</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Check uptime on all hosts:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ ansible -m shell -a 'uptime' all</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Check uname on all hosts:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ ansible -m shell -a 'uname -a' all</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Run playbook on more than one host:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ ansible-playbook playbook1.yml  -l 'host1.com,host2com'</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Enable Debug and Increase Verbosity in Ansible</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ ANSIBLE_DEBUG=true ANSIBLE_VERBOSITY=4 ansible-playbook playbook.yml</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_ansible.html'>ansible</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/ansible-cheatsheet19575.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./ansible-cheatsheet19575.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 20:16:47 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Mounting an ISO Image as a File System
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>If you need to get one or more files from an ISO image and don’t have
a CD/DVD drive you can mount the ISO image to a directory and navigate
to the file(s) you need using a terminal or file explorer. You’ll have
to do this as <em>root</em>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># mkdir /mnt/iso</code><br/>
<code># mount -o loop -t iso9660 /home/user/Downloads/Custom-Build/custom.iso /mnt/iso</code><br/>
<code>mount: /mnt/iso: WARNING: source write-protected, mounted read-only.</code><br/>
<code># cd /mnt/iso/</code><br/> <code># ls</code><br/>
<code>DateBuilt  System/  boot/  boot.catalog  efi.img  initrd  linux  mach_kernel  slint.txt</code><br/>
<code>#</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>When you’re done just unmount the location:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># umount /mnt/iso/</code><br/> <code>#</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_mount.html'>mount</a>, <a href='tag_iso.html'>iso</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/mounting-an-iso-image-as-a-file-system14927.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./mounting-an-iso-image-as-a-file-system14927.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2023 17:03:46 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Using sSMTP on Slackware 15.0
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p><strong>How to Install and Use ssmtp to Send Emails from the Linux
Terminal</strong></p>
<p>ssmtp is a simple utility that can be used to send emails from a
Linux system to a specified email address. It is just an MTA (Mail
Transfer Agent); it does not receive mail, expand aliases, or manage a
queue. Instead, it forwards automated emails to an external email
address. This can be useful for forwarding system alerts or other
automated emails from your system to an external email address.</p>
<p>According to the SlackBuild comments:</p>
<p>sSMTP, replaces sendmail on workstations that should send their mail
via the departmental mailhub from which they pick up their mail (via
pop, imap, rsmtp, pop_fetch, NFS… or the like). This program accepts
mail and sends it to the mailhub, optionally replacing the domain in the
From: line with a different one.</p>
<p>Normally, when using ssmtp, you want to remove the OS’s MTA
package(s), sendmail and/or postfix. In this case, ssmtp will be
symlinked to /usr/sbin/sendmail, and software that sends mail shouldn’t
have to be modified. If you keep sendmail/postfix installed, there’s no
conflict, but any software that sends mail will have to be configured or
modified to use /usr/sbin/ssmtp.</p>
<p>NOTE: After installing, you’ll want to edit “/etc/ssmtp/ssmtp.conf”.
There’s a man page for it (man ssmtp.conf).</p>
<p>In this post, we’ll show you how to install and use ssmtp to send an
email from the command-line interface.</p>
<p><strong>Step 1: Install ssmtp</strong></p>
<p>By default, the ssmtp package is not included in the default install
of Slackware but you can install it by running the following command if
you use sbotools:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># sboinstall ssmtp</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 2: Configure ssmtp</strong></p>
<p>Next, you’ll need to define your Gmail or other SMTP servers in the
ssmtp configuration file. You can do this by editing the
<code>/etc/ssmtp/ssmtp.conf</code> file:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>vim /etc/ssmtp/ssmtp.conf</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Add the following lines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>UseSTARTTLS=YES</code><br/>
<code>root=user@your-isp.com</code><br/>
<code>mailhub=smtp-mail.your-isp.com:587</code><br/>
<code>rewriteDomain=192.168.1.12</code><br/>
<code>hostname=192.168.1.12</code><br/>
<code>FromLineOverride=YES</code><br/>
<code>AuthUser=user@your-isp.com</code><br/>
<code>AuthPass=your-email-password</code><br/>
<code>AuthMethod=LOGIN</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Save and close the file when you’re finished. ssmtp is now configured
to use your SMTP server address to send an email.</p>
<p>Also modify the revaliases file in the same directory. A reverse
alias gives the From: address placed on a user’s outgoing messages and
(optionally) the mailhub these messages will be sent through.
Example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>root:jdoe@isp.com:mail.isp.com</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Messages root sends will be identified as from jdoe@isp.com and sent
through mail.isp.com.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ cat /etc/ssmtp/revaliases</code><br/>
<code># sSMTP aliases</code><br/> <code>#</code><br/>
<code># Format:    local_account:outgoing_address:mailhub</code><br/>
<code>#</code><br/>
<code># Example: root:your_login@your.domain:mailhub.your.domain[:port]</code><br/>
<code># where [:port] is an optional port number that defaults to 25.</code><br/>
<code>user:user@your-isp.com:smtp.your-isp.com:587</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Step 3: Send an Email with ssmtp</strong></p>
<p>First, create a text file and write some content:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>vim file.txt</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Add the following lines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>Subject: This is Subject Line</code><br/> <code></code><br/>
<code>Email content line 1</code><br/>
<code>Email content line 2</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Save and close the file, then send an email with attachment
<code>file.txt</code> to the external address
<code>user@your-isp.com</code>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>ssmtp -v user@your-isp.com &lt; file.txt</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>If everything is fine, you should see output indicating that the
email was sent successfully.</p>
<p>And that’s it! You’ve successfully installed and used ssmtp to send
an email from the Linux terminal. This can be a useful tool for sending
automated emails from your system to an external email address.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_ssmtp.html'>ssmtp</a>, <a href='tag_email.html'>email</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/using-ssmtp-on-slackware-150.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./using-ssmtp-on-slackware-150.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 18:36:09 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
How To Get Information on Linux
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>The <em>manpages</em> are historically <strong>the place to
go</strong> for any information about the software and utilities
installed on a Linux machine. I believe that the <em>info</em> page
seems to be the best place for <em>newbies</em> to go because it is so
much easier to navigate, and, like <em>manpages</em>, it is a still a
great place to get information about your system.</p>
<p>Suppose you want to get information about <em>socket</em>. You would
type:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ info socket</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>and you’d get a page that looks similar to a <em>manpage</em> but it
can be navigated by using keyboard shortcuts:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code></code>q<code>- exits back to the shell</code><br/>
<code></code>u<code>- moves up one level</code><br/>
<code></code>n<code>- moves to the next node on the current level</code><br/>
<code></code>p<code>- moves to the previous node on the current level</code><br/>
<code></code>space<code>- goes to the selected node under the cursor</code><br/>
<code></code>H<code>- lists all of the Info commands</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The commands <em>whatis</em> and <em>whereis</em> are also very
useful in finding information on the system.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ whatis printf</code><br/>
<code>printf (3)           - formatted output conversion</code><br/>
<code>printf (1)           - format and print data</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <em>whatis</em> command will list the set of manpages for a
specific keyword. The keyword <em>printf</em> is used in the
<em>bash</em> shell as well as the <em>c</em> programming language. Here
you see separate pages for each usage. To view them you would specify
the section number in your command to <em>man</em>, i.e.,
<code>$ man 3 printf</code> or <code>man printf</code> (which defaults
to section 1). This is the same output as entering
<code>$ man -f printf</code>.</p>
<p>The <em>whereis</em> command will list which system files reference a
specified keyword or command. For example,</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ whereis socket</code><br/>
<code>socket: /usr/man/man7/socket.7.gz /usr/man/mann/socket.n.gz /usr/man/man2/socket.2.gz</code><br/>
<code>$ whereis printf</code><br/>
<code>printf: /usr/bin/printf /bin/printf /usr/man/man3/printf.3.gz /usr/man/man1/printf.1.gz</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In case you aren’t really sure of what you’re looking for you can use
a ‘keyword’ search to the <em>man</em> or <em>apropos</em> commands
which will use the <em>keyword</em> you enter as a <em>regex</em>
(regular expression) to find all of the matches throughout the
manpages:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>$ man -k printf</code><br/>
<code>aa_printf (3)        - print text to AA-lib output buffers.</code><br/>
<code>asprintf (3)         - print to allocated string</code><br/>
<code>ber_printf (3)       - OpenLDAP LBER simplified Basic Encoding Rules library routines f...</code><br/>
<code>BIO_printf (3)       - formatted output to a BIO</code><br/>
<code>BIO_snprintf (3)     - formatted output to a BIO</code><br/>
<code>BIO_vprintf (3)      - formatted output to a BIO</code><br/>
<code>BIO_vsnprintf (3)    - formatted output to a BIO</code><br/>
<code>buffer_printf.c (3)  - Buffer management functions.</code><br/>
<code>curl_mprintf (3)     - formatted output conversion</code><br/>
<code>dprintf (3)          - formatted output conversion</code><br/>
<code>format (n)           - Format a string in the style of sprintf</code><br/>
<code>fprintf (3)          - formatted output conversion</code><br/>
<code>etc...</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In case you are interested, the <em>manpages</em> are broken down
into different sections as listed here:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>1  General Commands</code><br/>
<code>2  System Calls and Error Numbers</code><br/>
<code>3  C Libraries</code><br/> <code>3p perl</code><br/>
<code>4  Devices and device drivers</code><br/>
<code>5  File Formats and config files</code><br/>
<code>6  Game instructions</code><br/>
<code>7  Miscellaneous information</code><br/>
<code>8  System maintenance</code><br/>
<code>9  Kernel internals</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_man.html'>man</a>, <a href='tag_apropos.html'>apropos</a>, <a href='tag_whereis.html'>whereis</a>, <a href='tag_whatis.html'>whatis</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/how-to-get-information-on-linux25688.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./how-to-get-information-on-linux25688.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 17:12:52 -0400</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Locking Down SSH User Access
</title><description><![CDATA[
<p>To secure your system, you shouldn’t allow root to login remotely.
Instead, if an admin needs to use the <em>root</em> account they should
login using their own account and then <code>su -</code> or
<code>sudo</code> to the <em>root</em> account as needed.</p>
<p>Edit the <code>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</code> file and change the
following lines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>PermitRootLogin no</code><br/>
<code>PermitEmptyPasswords no</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of these properties may be commented out in the file, so all
you’d need to do is remove the <em>#</em> sign.</p>
<p>Once these changes are made you should then restart ssh. On my system
this is done by:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code># /etc/rc.d/rc.sshd restart</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>After the restart your changes will be in affect. However, root can
still login “from the local terminal”.</p>
<p>You can go a step further and restrict only specific users access to
login via ssh. For example, if you wanted only <em>user1</em> and
<em>user2</em> the ability to login with ssh you can add a line to the
above file:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>AllowUsers user1 user2</code><br/></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Everyone except these two users will be denied access via ssh.</p>
<p>Tags: <a href='tag_cli.html'>cli</a>, <a href='tag_ssh.html'>ssh</a>, <a href='tag_ssh-config.html'>ssh-config</a>, <a href='tag_motd.html'>motd</a></p>
<!-- text end -->
]]></description><link>http://www.szumowski.org/locking-down-ssh-user-access947.html</link>
<guid>http://www.szumowski.org/./locking-down-ssh-user-access947.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Gregg Szumowski</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 17:56:03 -0400</pubDate></item>
</channel></rss>
